The chairman is the leader of the board.
He is also a non-executive director.
In some cases, the chairman could be an
independent non-executive director.
I'll speak about that in a minute.
However, the chairman is the leader of the
board.
He is also referred to as first amongst
equals.
One of the responsibilities that the chairman has
is to ensure that as much as possible,
all of the directors on the board contribute
effectively to the discussions on the board.
So to give an illustration of that, when
you have new directors on the board, there's
a tendency for them to sort of feel
like they need to understand the dynamics of
the board and might spend time, sometimes too
long a period, to get acclimatised and so
they remain quiet for a while.
The chairman's responsibility is to make them feel
comfortable and actually seek them out and have
them contribute effectively to discussions.
The chairman also acts as a link between
the board and management.
He or she essentially gives guidance to the
CEO or the MD, as we had spoken
about, and ensures that whatever information the board
wants to pass to management, as much as
possible, he acts as that link person.
There's tenure restriction on directors, I must say,
under the different codes of corporate governance, now
guidelines.
The Nigerian Code of Corporate Governance, which is
the one that I'll be referencing a lot
in the course of this session, does not
specify a tenure for the categories of directors
I've spoken about, i.e. the EDs and
the non-executive directors.
The specific sectoral codes, for instance the CBN
guidelines, fixes a maximum tenure of 12 years
for these categories of directors.
The third category of directors is the independent
non-executive director.
This category of directors are expected to serve
on the board for not longer than 9
years in the case of non-financial institutions
and 8 years in the case of financial
institutions.
Essentially, they bring a level of independence, not
just in the way they are appointed, which
is critical, but also in their own situations
as well.
So they're not expected to be representatives of
significant shareholders.
In fact, typically they're not expected to hold
shares in the company.
The Nigerian Code of Corporate Governance specifies a
minimum number of shares they can hold, which
is 0.01%, very minimal.
But best practise would stipulate that they shouldn't
even own shares in the business because they
bring independent judgments and they're not expected to
be that involved in the business.
The only connection they have with the business
is their directorship.
They also shouldn't have been regulators in the
last 5 years, they shouldn't have been employed
by the company in any capacity, either as
employees or as consultants.
The whole essence of having independent directors on
the board is to have a situation where
you don't have too much power residing in
either the executives or the shareholder representatives, i
.e. the non-executive directors.
Independent directors are critical to the composition of
the board because they bring independent judgement.
And that kind of conversation is important when
we're discussing things like remuneration, dividend to shareholders,
or proposals of management that seems to be
more tilted towards the requirements of management.
So they bring that balance to board discussions.
But the most critical part of the independence,
in my view, is the appointment process.
How are independent directors appointed?
Typically they are appointed through a rigorous process
that entails a consultant that would use the
criteria provided by the company to determine the
kinds of people that would fit into the
profile provided by the company.
But beyond the fact of their independence, independent
directors are also expected to bring some level
of expertise, some level of experience, whether it's
technology, whether it's marketing.
They also bring some skills to add to
the diversity of the board.